hi I'm Bret contus and I wanted to film
a 10-minute YouTube video that discusses
the determinance of power production now
when I say power production it could
mean a vertical jump it could mean um
max speed sprinting it could be you know
um torsional Power swinging or throwing
but um there are certain um things you
need to know about power production
ideally I'd have a 60 Minute time frame
to discuss all this stuff but since it's
going to be YouTube video I'm just going
to roll through it real quickly so I can
get it done in 10 minutes um first um
we're going to talk about anatomical um
factors body weight you know a a 400 lb
person probably isn't going to jump very
high so there's an ideal body weight
depending on this the skill that you
want to maximize your power production
for body composition in general you
don't want a lot of fat because fat
doesn't contract muscles do
anthropometry and somatotype um usually
people are well suited for a particular
skill um in general long legs um helps
you you know produce more speed
um tendon attachment points there was a
study done on Elite sprinters that
showed that they had ideal attachment
points for their Achilles tendons and uh
also they have larger fascal lengths in
their muscle fibers so it's very very
important um and that's really something
you can't change that's genetically
predetermined and then a cross-sectional
area of muscles in general the larger
the cross-sectional area of a particular
muscle the more force it can produce and
the more rate of force development um
the higher the RFD or rate of force
development okay moving on to
physiology fiber type distribution um
Elite athletes usually have higher
percentage of fast twitch muscle fibers
um and you can influence you can shift
it towards one or the other through
training but this is very genetically
predetermined as well hormonal status um
certain hormones like testosterone um
growth hormone you know igf1 even your
insulin sensitivity this is going to
determine how you know first of all it
can influence contractions and speed of
contraction but it also determines how
well you recover and like the type of
physique that you're going to build and
that's very you can influence it through
training but it's also very genetically
predetermined neural drive you know kind
of like turning on the muscles rapidly
um coordination and this is
neuromuscular coordination it's not just
like coordination like balance this just
means how well your nervous system you
know fires the the the motor units and
it has to do a lot with you know things
like rate coating and Inter and
intramuscular coordination and
synchronization um arousal someone who's
char chared up and has a lot of
adrenaline he's going to be able to
produce more power than someone who's
kind of calm and relaxed um adaptations
to loading okay Wolf's Law and Davis's
law Wolf's Law deals with bone Davis's
law deals with soft tissue but the type
of loading that you do repeatedly for
example say you're doing jumping and
squatting all the time well then your
bones and your soft tissue is going to
remodel themselves according to the load
that's placed upon it so it will
actually build up
you know structurally it will adapt to
better produce that that loading pattern
and it'll transfer Force better so you
want to make sure you're doing a lot of
activities with that same loading
pattern to make sure that your body um
architecturally um uh constructs itself
to best transfer forces through the
tissues and maximize um you know your
elastic response to a certain activity
tuning muscular tuning this is something
it's it's not very trainable but you
might be able to improve it a little bit
but this has to do with your contraction
relaxation sequences um Elite athletes
they're you know for example when you
sprint um you're down to 8/10 of a or 8
hunds of a second of ground contact your
muscles have to be able to contract very
rapidly and then relax very
rapidly uh internal body temperature
obviously if you're you want to be the
ideal internal body temperature to allow
for for maximum um contractions and you
know um uh firing patterns and things
like that and then finally Anor robic
efficiency some activities that are a
little bit longer in duration require a
huge anerobic
component and you know you need to make
sure that that energy system is
maximally developed okay moving on to
environmental factors the surface if you
are on you know a very spongy material
you're not going to be able to jump as
high as if you're on a a a harder
material but then you know the perfect
surface can help out with your maximum
power production so you want the right
amount of basically you know compliance
to let you transfer as much energy as
possible external temperature if it's
freezing cold you're probably not going
to be able to you know produce as much
power as if it's a little bit warmer um
the clothing and Footwear if you have
tons of clothing on on or if you have
crappy shoes you won't get as much out
of uh as much transfer and then wind
obviously if you're running this way and
the wind is coming this way that will
decrease your power production and then
gravity which is a constant here on
Earth it's 9.8 m/s squared um now
finally moving on to motor programs now
a lot of these are interrelated here but
with motor programs you want the right
blend of mobility and stability if
you're all bound up and stiff um then
you're not going to be able to move your
joints through a full range of motion
but you can also be hyper mobile and
have too much so you want the right
blend of mobility and then stability
would be like the ability of your
stabilizers to um fixate the joint and
and allow for maximum transfer and not
you know and minimize energy leaks which
I'll talk about in a second okay posture
and Joint
centration you want the proper posture
to be able to you know to to you don't
want your joints to be able to go from
one extreme to the other so your normal
range is right in the middle and then
you get maximum power transfer because
you have the correct posture and this
has a lot to do with your strength
balances which I'll talk about in a
second okay um that's next strength
balances all right in general you want
to have equal horizontal pushing and
pulling strength you want equal um knee
dominant and hip dominant strength
um you want equal vertical pushing and
pulling strength and these help um
create an optimal body posture you know
you want good glute strength so you're
um and good core strength to control
your lumbar spine so you minimize energy
leaks while you're producing power
intraabdominal pressure and
intrathoracic pressure if you are
breathing out while you're supposed to
be producing power you're not going to
transfer uh as much power effectively
you want the right amount of of pressure
you know holding a breath at the right
amount at the right time to allow for
that maximal it stabilize the spine and
it kind of lets you transfer power
better and in general like when you're
lifting weights you want to fill the
lungs with about 70% of your maximum
title volume um and then last on this is
mechanical stiffness and this has to do
with um structurally you know
architecturally your muscles and tendons
can become more stiff and this is
actually a good thing because because
you get more transfer and your muscles
don't move as much your joints don't
move through as much range of motion as
you touch the
ground okay moving on to conditioning
and these are the factors that you can
really improve upon in the weight room
maximum strength strength speed speed
strength maximum strength would be like
a limit squat strength speed would be
more like um you know maybe like a uh a
an explosive deadlift or something um
speed strength that would be more like a
jump squat or maybe a lighter power
snatch or something okay then there's
rate of force development and this is
probably the most important thing
because as you get more and more
explosive you have less and less time to
produce maximum power okay reactive
strength and this is also called
elasticity your ability to absorb and
then um you know transfer the energy
that you produce starting strength um
and then react relative strength
relative strength is very important
because that's your your maximum
strength divided by your body weight
which is hugely important U and then
strength speed or or and strength speed
and power endurance this comes into
Factor when you're doing more like
something like a 100 meter sprint where
there's an endurance component okay
speaking of strength there's different
types of strength there's concentric
Ecentric isometric strength and then the
there's it's strength is specific to the
range of motion the its direction
specific you know there's all T types of
pushing pulling twisting left to right
up and down and then it's also dependent
on the movements the muscles you know
you have your lower body your upper body
your core so you want to be strong all
over and these all blend into skill you
want to bring up your weak links and you
want to practice practice practice all
these things contribute to your maximum
power production and will help you get
the most out of your you know your your
training in the weight room